现在我们已经知道了一次性密码本
让我们讨论一下如何让一次性密码本
Now that we know about the one-time pad,
let's talk about making the one-time pad
变得更为实用，即所谓流密码技术
在这之前，我们一起
more practical using something called the
stream cypher. But before we do that,
快速回顾一下之前的内容
我提示大家一下密码的定义
let's do a quick review of where we were.
So let me just remind you that a cypher is
密码是一个三元组：密钥空间、明文空间
defined over a triple of sets called a key
space, a message space, and a cypher text
和密文空间。密码有一对有效算法E和D
bare space. And a cypher is a pair of
efficient algorithms called E and D; E
E是加密算法，D是解密算法
我们需要用到的性质仅仅是
stands for encryption and D stands for
decryption. And the only property that we
解密是加密的逆过程，换句话说
need to satisfy is that decryption is the
opposite of encryption. In other words if
如果我用某个密钥加密了明文M
然后我使用相同的密钥解密
I encrypt a message M using a particular
key. And I decrypt using the same key. I
我可以还原明文的
上一次我们看了一些易破解的密码
get back the original message. Last time
we looked at a couple of weak cyphers like
比如替换式密码和Vigenere密码
我们展示了它们都能被轻易破解
the substitution cypher and the Vigenere
cypher. We showed that all of them can be
所以大家永远不要使用它们
easily broken so you should never ever,
ever use those cyphers. Those were just
它们仅具有历史意义
然后我们看了第一个好的密码
for historical reference. And then we
looked at our first example of a good
叫做一次性密码本。我再提醒一下
一次性密码本是如何定义的
cypher, namely the one-time pad. So let me
just remind you how the one-time pad is
明文空间是所有位字符串的集合
defined. Basically the message space is
the set of all bit and bit strings. The
密文也都是位字符串，密钥也类似
cypher text is a set of all bit and bit
strings. And similarly, the key is the
为所有N位字符串，加密也是使用简单的异或
set of all N bit strings and the way we
encrypt is by a simple XOR to encrypt the
来加密明文。我们通过用密钥异或明文
来获取密文
message. We just XOR the message in the
key that gives us the cypher text. And
为了解密密文，我们只需再次异或
then to decrypt a cypher text, we just do
this XOR again and it's easier to show
我们容易验证异或满足
解密为加密的逆过程这一性质
by properties of XOR that in fact
decryption is the opposite of encryption.
然后我们讨论了这个引理，我们证明了
And then we talked about this lemma, in
fact, we proved it, that says that the
一次性密码本拥有完美的安全性
这意味着，如果你只是监听通信
one-time pad has perfect secrecy, which
means that if you're just an eavesdropper
截获一段密文，你将无法破解
and you just get to see a single cypher
text, you're not going to be able to
以获得任何关于明文的信息，不幸的是
deduce any information about the encrypted
plain text. Unfortunately, we also said
我们还说Shannon证明了一个
充满坏消息的引理
that Shannon proved this lema, we called
it the bad news lema, that basically says
即任何完美安全的密码必须有足够长的密钥
that any cypher that has perfect secrecy
must have really long keys. In other
换句话说，密钥长度至少和明文一样长
words, the key length must be at least as
long as the length of the message, which
这意味着这种密码根本不实用
因为如果通信双方能够
means that the cypher is not particularly
useful. Because if two parties have a way
安全通信和明文一样长的密钥
to agree on really long keys that are as
long as the message, they, in some sense,
某种意义上他们可以使用这种机制直接通信
might as well use that mechanism to
already transmit the message itself. So in
所以这节讲座我们将使用一次性密码本的思想
this lecture we're going to take the idea
of the one time pad and try to make it
将其改造成一个实用的加密机制
这就是流密码
into a practical encryption scheme. So
this is called what's called a stream
在流密码中，密钥不是完全随机的
cypher. So the idea in this stream cypher
is rather than using a totally random key,
我们将使用一种伪随机密钥
we're actually going to use a
pseudo-random key. And to explain how that
为进一步解释，我需要定义什么是
伪随机数发生器(PRG)
works, I need to define what is a
pseudo-random generator, PRG. So a PRG,
PRG是一个函数，我取名g，意为发生器
really, all it is, is just a function,
I'll call it g for generator, that takes a
这个函数取一个种子为输入
我用｛0,1｝^s表示所有长度为s的字符串
seed, so I'm going to use zero one to the
s to denote all strings of length s, so
那么这个我们叫做种子空间
它将s位种子映射到一个
this we'll call the seed space. So he
takes an s bit seed and maps it to a much
长得多的字符串｛0,1｝^n
larger string which will denote by zero
one to the n. And the property is that n
这里n远远大于s。换句话说
我们的种子可能只有128位
must be much larger than s. So in other
words, we take a seed that might be only
但我们把它扩展成一个长得多的字符串
128 bits and we expand it into a much,
much larger output string that could be
可能有数G长度。这就是
伪随机数发生器的工作原理
gigabytes long. That's what this
pseudo-random generator does. And of
当然，发生器首先应当是能有效计算的
course, the goal is that first of all, the
generator is efficiently computable, so
所以应当有一些有效算法能计算函数g
the function g. There should be some sort
of an efficient algorithm that computes
也就是能被一确定性算法有效地计算
it. So, efficiently computable by a
deterministic algorithm. It's important to
函数g本身没有随机性，这点很重要
understand that the function g itself has
no more randomness, in it, it's a totally
函数g是完全确定的。这里唯一具有随机性的
就是这个随机种子
deterministic. The only thing that's
random here is the random seed, that's
它是作为函数g的输入
当然，另一性质是
given as input to the function g. And the
other property, of course, is that the
输出应当看起来是随机的
问题是“看起来是随机的”是什么意思？
output should look random and the
question is what does it mean to look
我们在本讲稍后给出这个的定义
random, and that's something we'll define
later on in the lecture. Okay so suppose
好的，假设我们有一发生器
我们如何使用它来构建一个流密码？
we have such a generator, how do we use
that, to build a stream cipher? Well the
方法是使用这个种子作为我们的密钥
idea is that we're gonna use the seed, as
our key, so our short seed is gonna be our
以种子为私钥，使用发生器将种子
secret key. And then we're gonna use the
generator to basically expand the seed
扩张成长得多的看起来很随机的序列
或称为伪随机序列
into a much, much larger random looking
sequence, or pseudo random sequence, as
由于算法已知，所以可写作G(K)
然后我们将进行异或操作
it's known, so this would be G of K. And then
we are going to XOR it just like in the
就像一次性密码本一样
我们将伪随机序列和明文异或
one time pad we're going to XOR the
pseudo random sequence with the message
得到密文。如果我们用数学表示之
and that's going to give us the cypher
text. Or if we want to write this in math,
即为C是M与K的加密
we'll write C equals the encryption of the
message M with a key K, which is simply
即为M与G(K)的简单异或。当我们想解密时
我们就做同样的事情
defined as M XOR G of K. And then when we
want to decrypt, basically we do exactly
就是密文异或G(K)，就像一次性密码本
the same thing. It's basically the cypher
text XOR G of K, just like in the one-time
只不过不是与密钥K异或，而是与
发生器对K的输出结果异或
pad except then instead of XOR-ing with K,
we XOR with the output of the generator
那么第一个问题就是，为什么这是安全的？
applied to K. So the first question to ask
is why is it secure? So, basically you
目前，我们只有一种安全的观念，叫做完美安全
now, we only have one notion of security
so far, which we called perfect secrecy.
那么一个流密码是完美安全吗？
And so let's just quickly ask can a stream
cipher have perfect secrecy. Remember in
注意在流密码中，密钥比明文短得多
the stream cipher the key is much, much
shorter than the message. And so,
即便如此，可能是完美安全吗？答案是否定的
nevertheless can it have perfect secrecy? So
I hope everybody said the answer is, no.
密钥比明文短得多，我们说在完美安全的密码中
The key is much shorter than the message.
And we said that in a, in a perfectly
密钥至少和明文一样长
secure cypher, the key must be as long as
the message. And therefore, it's not
所以流密码不可能是完美安全的
possible that a, that a stream cypher
actually has perfect secrecy. So the
问题是，为什么我们还说流密码是安全的呢？
首先我们需要一个不同的关于安全的定义
question is, then, well, why is it secure?
First of all we would need a different
来论证流密码的安全性
definition of security to argue that
stream cypher is, is secure and in
特别地，安全性依赖于我们使用的特别的发生器
particular, the security property is going
to depend on the specific generator that
事实上，我们需要隐私的定义来论证
we used. So in fact the definition of
privacy that we'll need to argue the
流密码的隐私安全，我们将在下一讲介绍
security of Stream Cipher is we'll see in
the next lecture, but for now let me show
现在我给大家一个特别的性质
安全的发生器所必须有的性质
you one particular property. That a
generator must have a minimum property
这个性质叫不可预测性
needed for security. This property is
called unpredictability. So let's
我们设想一下如果一个流密码是可预测的
suppose for one second that in fact a
stream cycle is predictable. So, what does
什么意思？PRG是可预测的
即存在某个数I
that mean? Both the PRG is predictable.
What that means is essentially that there
如果我们给PRG输出的前I位
is some i. Such that if I give you the
first I bits of the outputs. This notation
这个记号表示看函数输出的前I位
Bar one to I means look at the first
I-bits of the output of the function.
好，如果我们给生成流的前I位
存在某种算法
Okay, so I give you the first I bits of
the stream. There is some sort of an
一种有效的算法，可以计算余下的字符串
algorithm, there's an efficient algorithm
that will compute the rest of the string.
好的，给定前I位，你能计算出余下的位
Okay, so given the first I bits, you can
compute the remainder of the bits. I claim
我觉得如果是这种情况，
那么这个流密码是不安全的
that if this is the case, then the stream
cypher would not be secure. So let's see
为什么？设想攻击者截获了一段密文
why. Suppose an attacker actually
intercepts a particular cypher text, let's
即为C。如果是这种情况，就会有问题
call it c. If this is the case, then in
fact, we have a problem. Because suppose
因为基于一些预知的知识
that just by some prior knowledge, the
attacker actually knows that the initial
攻击者知道信息的某些部分最初的明文内容
举个例子
part of the message happens to be some
known value. For example, we know that in
因特网电子邮件标准协议之一SMTP
the mail protocol, smtp, the standard mail
call used in the internet, you know that
大家知道这个协议里每条信息都以from;开头
那就是攻击者预先知道的前缀
every message starts with a word from
colon. Well, that would be a prefix that
信息必须以from；开头
the adversary knows. That the site, that
the message must begin with from a colon.
攻击者可以将from；的密文
What it could do is it could XOR
the cipher text with the words from colon,
与事先预知的明文异或
with the little prefix of the message that
it actually knows. And what that would
得到的就是伪随机序列的前缀
give it is a prefix of, of the pseudo
random sequence. And I would learn as a
我能知道伪随机序列的前缀
result of this, it would learn a prefix of
the pseudo random sequence but then we
由于一旦知道伪随机序列的前缀
know that once it has a prefix of the
pseudo random sequence it can predict the
我们就可以预测伪随机序列的剩余部分
remainder of the pseudo random sequence
and that would allow it to then predict
也就是说我们能预测出明文的剩余部分
这个例子说明如果伪随机序列是可预测的
the rest of the message. Okay, so for
example if the pseudo random generator was
给定序列的前5位，那么这个用流密码加密的
predictable given five bits of the pad.
Then every email encrypted using the
邮件就是可以被破解的，再说一遍
stream cypher would be decryptable
because, again, the attacker knows the
攻击者知道明文的前缀，推出伪随机序列的前缀
prefix of the message from which he
deduces the prefix of the pad, which then
进而计算出序列的其他部分，从而还原整个明文
allows him to compute the rest of the pad,
which then allows him to recover the
所以这个例子证实了如果一个PRG可预测
entire plain text. Okay, so this is an
example that shows that in fact if a PRG
就有安全问题。因为前缀会暴露整个信息
is predictable then already there are
security problems. Because a small prefix
即使我只能预测输出序列的一位
would reveal the entire message. As it
turns out, even if I could just predict
即使给定前I位的输出，我能预测下一位
one bit of the outputs. Even if given, you
know, the first I bits, I can predict the
第I+1位，这也有问题，因为新的前缀又有了
next bit, the I plus first bit. Already,
this is a problem. Because that would say
也就是信息的前缀可以被预测和解密
that given again, the first couple of
letters in a message can predict, can
进而还原信息中的下一位，或是下一字母，等等
decrypt essentially, and recover the next
bit of the message, or the next letter of
所以这个可预测性告诉我们
the message, and so on. So this
predictability property shows that, you
如果我们在流密码中使用PRG
know, if we use a PRG that's going to be
used in a stream cypher, it had better be
它最好是不可预测的。PRG不可预测是什么意思？
unpredictable. So what does it mean that a
PRG is unpredictable? So let's define more
让我们给出不可预测性的更多定义
precisely what it means for a PRG to be
unpredictable. Well first we'll define
我们先定义PRG可预测的意义
more precisely what it means for a PRG to
be predictable. So we say that G is
我们说G是可预测的，如果存在一个有效算法
我们将该算法记为A，还有一个位置
predictable, if there exists an efficient
algorithm. Let's call it A and there is
有一个位置为I，位于0到N-1之间
some position. There's a position I
between one and N minus one such that if
如果我们看分布在随机密钥上的概率
we look at the probability over a random
key. Probability if I generate a random
我生成一个随机密钥，这个记号表示
从密钥空间K中随机选取一个密钥
key. You remember, this notation means
choose a random key from the set K. So
那么这个带r的箭头表示
从K中随机选取一个密钥
this arrow with r just means choose a
random key from the set K. Basically, if I
如果我把输出前缀输入给这个算法
我给输出的前I个字节
give this algorithm the prefix of the
output, if I give it the first I bytes of
该算法能预测出下一位的概率
the output, the probability that it's able
to predict the next bit of the outputs,
大于1/2加上Epislon
this probability is greater than half plus
epislon. For some non-negligible. For some
对于一些不可忽略的量，表示为Epsilon
non-negligible, epsilon. A non-
negligible, for example, would be
比如Epsilon大于2的负30次方
也就是十亿分之一
epsilon, which is greater than one over
two to the 30. One over a billion, for
我们并不认为它是可忽略的
那么我们将在本讲稍后来讨论
example, we would consider it not
negligible. So these terms, negligible and
可忽略与不可忽略，并给出更精确的定义
non negligible will come back at the end
of the lecture, and define them more
现在我们继续使用不可忽略的直观概念
precisely. But for now, let's just, stick
with the intuitive notion of what non
一个发生器算法
negligible means. And so this is what it
means, for an algorithm, for a generator
如果它是可预测的，存在某个算法能够预测
to be, predictable. Basically, there is
some algorithm that is able to predict the
第I+1位，在给定前缀的前提下，对吧？
然后我们说，一个算法
I plus first bit, given the mutual prefix,
okay? And then we say that an algorithm,
PRG是不可预测的，事实上
that a PRG is unpredictable. If in
fact, well, if it doesn't satisfy the
这样的算法不满足这里定义的性质
换句话说，它是不可预测的
property that we just defined. In other
words, it is not predictable. But what
不可预测的更为精确的定义是
does it mean, more precisely for it not to
be predictable. It means that, in fact,
对于各个位置，即对所有i，
没有有效的破解算法A
for all positions, for all i there is
no efficient adversary no efficient
以不可忽略的概率预测出第i+1位
algorithm A that can predict the i + 1
bit with non negligible probability.
很好。这个对所有i都成立，
不管给定什么样的前缀
Excellent. Okay and this has to be true
for all I. So no matter which prefix I
你也无法成功预测出前缀的下一位
give you, you're not gonna be able to
predict the next bit that follows the
那么让我们看几个例子
这是一个很傻瓜的例子
prefix. Okay, so let's look at some
examples. Here is a silly, silly example.
我给你一个发生器，
问你它是可预测的吗？
Suppose I give you a generator, and I ask
you, is it predictable? Well, this
这个发生器具有这样的性质：
如果我计算输出的所有位的异或
generator happens to have the property,
that if I XOR all the bits of the
我总能得到1，好，我计算所有位
outputs, I always happen to get one. Okay,
so I XOR all the bits. Bit number one,
（回顾：奇偶校验）
第一位异或第二位，再异或第三位
如果我将所有位全部异或
XOR bit number two, XOR bit number
three. If I XOR all those bits, I
我可以得到1。问题是，
这个发生器是可预测的吗？
happen to get one. The question is, is
that a predictable generator? And again, I
我希望大家都认为“是”
本质上，给定输出前n-1位
hope everybody answered yes, that
essentially given the first n minus one
我可以预测出第n位，因为要
满足前n位的异或必须是1
bits of the outputs, I can predict the nth
bit because it would just be the bits
换句话说，我给你发生器的输出
that's needed to make the XOR all the
bits be one. In other words, I give you
除了最后一位，你是可以预测出
发生器输出的最后一位的
all but one of the bits of the generator,
you can actually predict the last bit of
我们既然已经看到PRG必须是不可预测的
the generator. Now that we've seen that
PRGs have to be unpredictable, I just want
我只想提几个脆弱的PRG
它们永远不应在密码学中使用
to mention a couple of weak PRGs that
should never ever be used for crypto. This
这是个常见错误，我希望确保
大家不要犯这些错误
is a very common mistake and I just want
to make sure none of you guys make this
一种常见的、加密时不能使用的PRG
mistake. So a very common PRG that should
actually never be used for crypto is
叫做线性同余方法
我稍微解释一下
called a linear congruential generator. So
let me explain what a linear congruential
线性同余方法有三个参数，
分别叫做A，B,和P
generator is. Basically it has parameters.
It has three parameters. I'll call them A,
A和B是整数，P是一个质数
我们如下定义发生器
B and P. A and B are just integers and P
is a prime. And the generator is defined
我引入R0作为发生器的种子
as follows, essentially I'll say R zero is
the seed of the generator. And then the
然后生成随机数的方法就是
迭代地运行下面的步骤
way you generate randomness is basically
you iteratively run through the following
计算A乘以R(i-1)加上B，再取模P
steps. You compute a times r of I minus
one plus b modular p. Then you output a
然后输出几位关于目前状态i的数Ri
few bits of the current states, output few
bits of Ri. Then, of course, you
然后将i加一，再反复迭代之，怎么样？
increment I and you iterate this again and
again and again. Okay? So you can see how
这就是其如何工作的
从一个特定的种子开始
this generator proceeds. It starts with a
particular seed. At every step there is
每一步应用这个线性变换
this linear transformation that's being
applied to the seed. And then you output a
然后你输出目前状态Ri的几位
然后反复迭代。。。
few bits of the current state and then you
do that again and again and again and
不幸的是，尽管这个发生器
具有良好的统计学性质
again. Unfortunately even though this
generator has good statistical properties
比如说，输出的0的数目很可能
in the sense that, for example, the number
of zeroes it outputs is likely going to be
与1的数目差不多，等等；
实际上你可以证实
similar to the number of ones and so on;
it has, you can actually argue all sorts
一些漂亮的统计性质。
但是这个发生器很容易被预测
of nice statistical properties about this,
nevertheless it is a very easy generator
事实上它不应当被使用
如果给定一些输出
to predict. And in fact should never ever
be used. In fact, just given a few
一些输出的样本，是容易预测出
序列的剩余部分的
outputs, a few output samples, it's easy
to predict the remainder of the sequence.
因此，这个发生器不应当被使用的
And as a result, this generator should
never ever be used. Another example is a
另一个随机数发生器的例子与
线性同余方法很接近
random number generator that is very
closely related to the linear congruential
这也是glibc里使用的发生器
generator. This is a random number
generator implemented in glibc, very
(glibc: GNU C Library函数库)
非常常见，我写下了它的定义
common library. That you can see. I just
wrote down the definition here. You can
每轮输出几位数据
see that it basically outputs a few bits
at every iteration and it just does this
每轮都执行这个简单的线性变换
同样这个发生器非常容易预测
simple linear transformation at every
step. Again, this is a very easy generator
在加密中不应当被使用
to predict and should never ever be used
for crypto. And so the lesson I want to
所以我强调永远不要使用glibc库里的
随机生成函数
emphasize here is never ever use the
built-in glibc function random. For crypto,
因为它不能满足密码学的随机性
because it doesn't produce,
cryptographic randomness, in the sense
也就是不易预测性。事实上，
类似第四版Kerberos的系统
that it is easy to predict. And, in fact,
systems like Kerberos version four have
使用了这个函数，也已被破解了
所以，不要再犯错了
used random and, have been beaten by that.
So, please don't make that mistake
下一讲我们会讨论如何安全地
生成随机数
yourself. We will talk about how to do
secure random number generation actually in
结束本讲之前，我想给出
the next lecture. Before we conclude this
lecture I just want to give a little bit
关于可忽略和不可忽略的更多细节
more detail about these concepts of
negligible and non-negligible values, so
密码学界的不同圈子对这两概念的
定义有所不同
different communities in crypto actually
define these concepts differently, for
对于实用派来说，可忽略和不可忽略
practitioners basically these the term
negligible and non-negligible,
仅仅是定义里的特定值，例如
are just, particular scalers that are used in the
definition. So, for example, a
实用派认为，如果一个值
比十亿分之一大(2^-30)
practitioner would say, that if a value is
more than one over, one over a billion,
我们说这个值是不可忽略的
one over two to the 30, we say that the
value is non-negligible. The reason is,
原因是如果你使用密钥加密
the reason that's so, is, because if you
happen to use a key, for example, for, for
一个G的数据，约2^30字节
encrypting a gigabyte of data, a gigabyte
of data is about two to the 30 or maybe
或2^32字节，那么2^30分之一概率的事件
even two to the 32 bytes. Then an event
that happens with the probability one over
就会很有可能发生，
对于1个G的数据而言
two to the thirty will likely happen after
about a gigabyte of data. So since a
由于我们用一个G的数据来推断密钥
这个事件很有可能发生
gigabyte of data is within reason for a
particular key, this event is likely to
所以2^30分之一是不可忽略的
happen. Therefore one over two to the
thirty is non-negligible. On the other
另外，我们说2^80分之一
hand, we'll say that one over two to the
eighty. Which is much, much, much smaller
这是一个小得多的概率
is an event, an event that happens with
this probability is an event that's
在密钥使用过程中，这个小概率事件
将不太可能会发生
actually not going to happen over the life
of the key. And therefore we'll say that
我们说这是一个可忽略的事件
由此可见，这些关于
that's a negligible event. As it turns
out, these practical definitions of
可忽略与不可忽略的定义
其实是有点问题的
negligible and non-negligible are quite
problematic and we'll see examples of why
我们稍后再来看相关例子
事实上，更严格的密码学理论
they're problematic later on. So in fact
in the more rigorous theory of
可忽略与不可忽略的定义
有所不同
cryptography, the definition of negligible
and non-negligible are somewhat different.
事实上，当我们讨论事件概率时
And in fact, when we talk about the
probability of an event, we don't talk
我们不会对概率定值
而是把它看作是一个安全参数的函数
about these probabilities as scalers, but
rather we talk about them as functions of
让我来解释一下
a security parameter. So let me explain
what that means. So these functions,
这些函数本质上输出正实数
essentially, are functions that map, that
outputs, positive real values. So, are non
(注意有口误map)
这些非负实数被认为是概率
negative real values that are supposedly
probabilities. But they're functions that
函数的定义域为非负整数，怎么样？
那么不可忽略的函数如何呢？
act on non negative integers, okay? So,
what does it mean for a function to be
答案是函数值以无限的可能性
大于某个多项式的值
non-negligible? What it means is that the
function is bigger than some polynomial
换句话说，对于无穷多个值
infinitely often. In other words, for
many, for infinitely many values, the
函数值大于1除以某个多项式的值
function is bigger than some, one over
polynomial, okay? So I wrote the exact
我写下了严格定义，待会看一个例子
definition here, and we'll see an example,
in just a minute. Okay? So if something is
如果函数值经常大于1除以多项式的值
我们说它是不可忽略的
bigger, is often bigger than one of that
polynomial, we'll say that it's non-negligible.
不过，如果函数值小于所有多项式
对应的值，我们就说它是可忽略的
However, if something is
smaller than all polynomials, then we'll
这就是说，对于任何次数的多项式
say that it's negligible. So, what this
says here, basically, for any degree
对于任何d，存在某个下界Lambda_d
polynomial, for all d, there exists some
lower bound lambda-d such as, for all
对于任何比这个下界大的参数Lambda
函数总是小于1除以多项式的值
lambda bigger than this lambda-d, the
function is smaller than one over the
这说明了可忽略的函数值总是小于
polynomial. So all this says is that the
function is negligible if it's less than
各个多项式分式值。换句话说
总是小于1除以Lambda^d
all polynomial fractions. In other words, is
less than one over lambda-d for
对于充分大的Lambda总成立
让我们看几个例子
sufficiently large lambda. So let's look
at some examples. And we'll see
稍后我们会看到可忽略与
不可忽略的一些应用
applications of these negligible and
non-negligible concepts later on. But I
这里我们只是希望大家能明白
如何去准确理解这些概念
just want to make, wanted to make it clear
that this is how you would rigorously find
小于或大于1除以多项式
these concepts. Basically either smaller
than one over poly or bigger than one over
一个是可忽略，另一个不可忽略
poly, one would be negligible, the
other would be non-negligible. Let's look
看些例子。比如说，一个函数
随Lambda的增加指数级衰减
at some examples. So, for example, a
function that drops exponentially in
很明显这个函数是可忽略的
对于任意d，存在一个充分大的Lambda
lambda clearly would be negligible because
for any constant d there is a sufficiently
满足：1除以2的Lambda次方小于
1除以Lambda的d次方
large, large lambda. Such as one over two
to the lambda is less than one over lambda
好的，这显然比所有多项式分式小
to the d. Okay. So this is clearly less
than all polynomials. Over the function,
1除以Lambda的1000次方
这是一个增长极为缓慢的函数
say, one over lambda to a thousand, right.
This is a function that grows very, very,
它的值几乎不动
不过，这个函数不可忽略
very slowly. It barely ever moves.
Nevertheless, this function is
因为如果我取d为10000
non-negligible because if I set d to be
10,000, then clearly this function is
显然函数值大于
1除以Lambda的10000次方
bigger than one over lambda to the 10,000.
And so this function is bigger than some
这个函数值大于某个多项式分式
我们再看一个费解一点的例子
polynomial fraction. And let's look at a
confusing example, just to be tricky. What
你怎么想？设想我有一个函数
对于奇数lambda它是指数级小的
do you think? Suppose I have a function that for
an odd lambda it happens to be exponentially small,
对于偶数lambda它是多项式级小的
for even lambda, it happens to be
polynomially small. Is this a negligible or
它是可忽略还是不可忽略呢？
那么根据定义，它是
non-negligible function? Well, by our
definition this would a non-negligible
不可忽略的。直观地，这个函数
经常表现为多项式小
function. And the intuition is, if a
function happens to be only polynomially
实际上意味着这个事件
small, very often, that actually means
that this event, you know, an event
发生的概率已然太大了
无法满足实际加密的需要
that happens with this probability, is
already too large to be used in a real
这里需要记住的要点是这些术语
cryptosystem. Okay, so, the main points to
remember here, are that these terms,
小于多项式，大于多项式
basically, correspond to less than
polynomial or more than polynomial, but
但在本课程里，我们最常使用
小于指数来表示可忽略性
throughout the course, we'll mostly use
negligible to mean less than, than an
不可忽略意思是大于1除以多项式
exponential. And non-negligible to mean,
less than one over polynomial. So now we
（有口误less）
现在我们看了将一次性密码本
实用化的核心思想
saw the core idea for converting the one
time pad into a practical cipher. And I
也就是流密码。下一讲里
mean, the stream cipher. And then, in the
next lecture, we're gonna see how to
我们将证实流密码的安全性
actually argue that the stream cipher is
actually secure. That's gonna require a
需要引入安全的新定义，因为
完美安全在这里不是很好
new definition of security, since perfect
secrecy is not good enough here, and we
那么我们下一讲见
will see that in the next lecture.